<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>shocks | Karol Fulat</title><link>https://KFulat.github.io/tag/shocks/</link><atom:link href="https://KFulat.github.io/tag/shocks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>shocks</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://KFulat.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>shocks</title><link>https://KFulat.github.io/tag/shocks/</link></image><item><title>SNRs shock waves with turbulent upstream medium</title><link>https://KFulat.github.io/project/snr_shocks/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://KFulat.github.io/project/snr_shocks/</guid><description>&lt;p>Investigating shock wave properties in supernova remnants (SNRs) is of a major importance in understanding the origin and acceleration of cosmic rays. For Diffusive Shock Acceleration electrons must have a highly suprathermal energy, implying a need for very efficient pre-acceleration. Most published studies consider a homogeneous upstream medium, which is an unrealistic assumption for astrophysical environments. Using 2D3V particle-in-cell simulations, we investigate electron acceleration and heating processes at high Mach-number shocks with a turbulent upstream medium. For this purpose slabs of plasma with compressive turbulence are separately simulated and then inserted into shock simulations, which requires matching of plasma slabs at the interface. Using a novel technique of matching electromagnetic fields and currents, we perform simulations of perpendicular shocks setting different intensities of density fluctuations in the upstream. We explore the impact of the fluctuations on electron heating, the dynamics of upstream electrons, and the driving of plasma instabilities. Our results indicate that while the presence of the turbulence enhances variations in the upstream magnetic field, their levels remain too low to influence significantly the behaviour of electrons at perpendicular shocks.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Electron acceleration at shocks in merging galaxy clusters</title><link>https://KFulat.github.io/project/cluster-shocks/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://KFulat.github.io/project/cluster-shocks/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this thesis we investigate conditions for effective electron injection at low Mach number
galaxy cluster shocks. In particular, we discuss the effects of multi-scale magnetic field turbu-
lence at the shock, that includes the shock surface rippling. We study the role of the rippling in
the electron pre-acceleration to DSA. The main tool used in this study is a numerical technique
of particle-in-cell (PIC) simulations, which is an ab-intitio method for collisionless plasma.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Suprathermal electrons at interplanetary shocks</title><link>https://KFulat.github.io/project/electrons/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://KFulat.github.io/project/electrons/</guid><description>&lt;p>The stream of particles known as the solar wind spreads out within the heliosphere, creating shocks. These waves are collisionless, meaning that energy transfer between particles is via collective particle-waves interactions instead of binary Coulomb collisions. Interplanetary shocks (IP) originate from co-rotating interaction regions, areas where the fast solar wind rams into the slow one, and from coronal mass ejections, which are huge releases of solar plasma. The distribution function of the solar wind electrons is strongly influenced by these shocks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Suprathermal electrons have energies of about 70 eV to 2 keV and they follow the interplanetary magnetic field line as they propagate through the heliosphere. This means that their pitch-angle distributions contain information about the magnetic topology of the solar wind.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The project aimed to characterise and examine suprathermal electron populations associated with IP shocks. We used electron angle-angle distributions, measured in situ by the Cluster spacecrafts, during normal solar wind conditions, in the presence of whistler waves and during events associated with IP shocks. The shape of the distributions was examined using spectra of fitted spherical harmonics. This method is a quick way to characterise observed spectra and can be used for Solar Orbiter data, allowing us to study the evolution of the distributions during the propagation at an IP shock.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>