<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Projects | Karol Fulat</title><link>https://KFulat.github.io/project/</link><atom:link href="https://KFulat.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Projects</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://KFulat.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Projects</title><link>https://KFulat.github.io/project/</link></image><item><title>SNRs shock waves with turbulent upstream medium</title><link>https://KFulat.github.io/project/snr_shocks/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://KFulat.github.io/project/snr_shocks/</guid><description>&lt;p>The origin and acceleration mechanisms of cosmic rays, the energetic charged particles that reach the Earth&amp;rsquo;s surface, is still an open question in modern astrophysics. Observations of radio emission, nonthermal X-rays and high-energy gamma-rays from supernova remnants (SNR) indicate the efficient electron acceleration there. The particles are though to gain energy at collisionless and non-relativistic shock waves that form during supernova explosions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The widely known mechanism of particle acceleration at shocks is Diffusive Shock Acceleration, in which particles gain energy by crossing a shock multiple times. However, the particles must have initial energy to be able to participate in this process. This means that electrons must have highly suprathermal energy, which implies the need for very efficient pre-acceleration, known as the electron injection problem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Studies of complex particle dynamics in plasma on an electron kinetic scale requires the use of the particle-in-cell approach: first-principles simulations for collisionless plasma. Even with the power of modern supercomputers, these numerical experiments are computationally demanding.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Currently, our project consists of the following parts: understanding the electron injection at oblique SNR shocks and investigating the influence of pre-existing turbulence on the electron acceleration.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Electron acceleration at shocks in merging galaxy clusters</title><link>https://KFulat.github.io/project/cluster-shocks/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://KFulat.github.io/project/cluster-shocks/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this thesis we investigate conditions for effective electron injection at low Mach number
galaxy cluster shocks. In particular, we discuss the effects of multi-scale magnetic field turbu-
lence at the shock, that includes the shock surface rippling. We study the role of the rippling in
the electron pre-acceleration to DSA. The main tool used in this study is a numerical technique
of particle-in-cell (PIC) simulations, which is an ab-intitio method for collisionless plasma.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Suprathermal electrons at interplanetary shocks</title><link>https://KFulat.github.io/project/electrons/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://KFulat.github.io/project/electrons/</guid><description>&lt;p>The stream of particles known as the solar wind spreads out within the heliosphere, creating shocks. These waves are collisionless, meaning that energy transfer between particles is via collective particle-waves interactions instead of binary Coulomb collisions. Interplanetary shocks (IP) originate from co-rotating interaction regions, areas where the fast solar wind rams into the slow one, and from coronal mass ejections, which are huge releases of solar plasma. The distribution function of the solar wind electrons is strongly influenced by these shocks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Suprathermal electrons have energies of about 70 eV to 2 keV and they follow the interplanetary magnetic field line as they propagate through the heliosphere. This means that their pitch-angle distributions contain information about the magnetic topology of the solar wind.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The project aimed to characterise and examine suprathermal electron populations associated with IP shocks. We used electron angle-angle distributions, measured in situ by the Cluster spacecrafts, during normal solar wind conditions, in the presence of whistler waves and during events associated with IP shocks. The shape of the distributions was examined using spectra of fitted spherical harmonics. This method is a quick way to characterise observed spectra and can be used for Solar Orbiter data, allowing us to study the evolution of the distributions during the propagation at an IP shock.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>