<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>acceleration | Karol Fulat</title><link>https://KFulat.github.io/tag/acceleration/</link><atom:link href="https://KFulat.github.io/tag/acceleration/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>acceleration</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://KFulat.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>acceleration</title><link>https://KFulat.github.io/tag/acceleration/</link></image><item><title>Kinetic simulations of perpendicular supernova remnant shocks propagating in turbulent medium</title><link>https://KFulat.github.io/publication/fulat_2023_apj/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://KFulat.github.io/publication/fulat_2023_apj/</guid><description>&lt;!--
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em>Slides&lt;/em> button to check out the example.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
Supplementary notes can be added here, including [code, math, and images](https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/). --></description></item><item><title>Pre-acceleration in the Electron Foreshock. II. Oblique Whistler Waves</title><link>https://KFulat.github.io/publication/morris_2023_apj/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://KFulat.github.io/publication/morris_2023_apj/</guid><description>&lt;!--
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Click the &lt;em>Cite&lt;/em> button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em>Slides&lt;/em> button to check out the example.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
-->
&lt;p>Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href="https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">code, math, and images&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Electron acceleration at shocks in supernova remnants</title><link>https://KFulat.github.io/project/snr_shocks/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://KFulat.github.io/project/snr_shocks/</guid><description>&lt;div style='text-align: justify;'>
The origin and acceleration mechanisms of cosmic rays, the energetic charged particles that reach the Earth's surface, is still an open question in modern astrophysics. Observations of radio emission, nonthermal X-rays and high-energy gamma-rays from supernova remnants (SNR) indicate the efficient electron acceleration there. The particles are though to gain energy at collisionless and non-relativistic shock waves that form during supernova explosions.&lt;br/>&lt;br/>
The widely known mechanism of particle acceleration at shocks is Diffusive Shock Acceleration, in which particles gain energy by crossing a shock multiple times. However, the particles must have initial energy to be able to participate in this process. This means that electrons must have highly suprathermal energy, which implies the need for very efficient pre-acceleration, known as the electron injection problem.&lt;br />
Studies of complex particle dynamics in plasma on an electron kinetic scale requires the use of the particle-in-cell approach: first-principles simulations for collisionless plasma. Even with the power of modern supercomputers, these numerical experiments are computationally demanding.&lt;br />
&lt;p>Currently, our project consists of the following parts: understanding the electron injection at oblique SNR shocks and investigating the influence of pre-existing turbulence on the electron acceleration.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>